Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
John Davis Hatch papers
1790-1995
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Hatch, John Davis
24.9 linear feet
The papers of art historian, collector, educator, and museum administrator John Davis Hatch measure 24.9 linear feet and date from 1790-1995. Within the papers are biographical materials; correspondence; personal business and legal documents; diaries; research, organization, and teaching files; writings; printed materials; photographs; and works of art (mostly sketches) by American artists. Research files regarding artists and specific subjects comprise the bulk of this collection.
Provenance
John Davis Hatch and the John Davis Hatch estate donated his papers to the Archives of American Art in several installments between 1960-1996. Many of the primary materials relating to John Vanderlyn were acquired by Hatch from a photographer in Kingston, New York who received them from a niece of Vanderlyn. Robert Graham of James Graham and Sons gave Vanderlyn's will to Hatch.
Separated Material
Four books annotated by Bluemner, a letter from Bluemner, a letter from A. Stieglitz to Bluemner, photographs of works of art, and exhibition materials were removed from the papers and merged with the Oscar Bluemner papers at the Archives of American Art.
Related Material
The Archives of American Art holds two oral history interviews with John Davis Hatch: June 8, 1964 conducted by H. Wade White and 1979-1980 conducted by Robert F. Brown. Also found is a separately cataloged photograph of Hatch and Henry Francis Taylor from 1933.
Additional research materials complied by Hatch are located in the Albany Institute of History and Art, the Metropolitan Museum, the library of the National Gallery of Art, and the Senate House, Kingston, New York.
Hatch donated two hundred and seventy American drawings to the National Gallery of Art in Washington, D.C.
Alternative Forms Available
Twenty sketches from the collection are available on 35 mm microfilm reel 2814 at Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan.
Restrictions on Access
Use of originals requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Art historian, collector, educator, and museum administrator John Davis Hatch (1907-1996) worked in the Boston and New England area, as well as the Pacific Northwest, and New York state. Hatch served as director of the Art Institute of Seattle, the Isabella Stewart Gardner Museum, the Albany Institute of Art and History, and the Norfolk Museum of Art and Sciences.
John Davis Hatch was born in San Francisco, California in 1907. His father, grandfather, and great-grandfather were architects and Hatch studied landscape architecture at the University of California, Berkeley. He served as an apprentice to Lockwood de Forest. After abandoning landscape architecture, he accepted a position as director of the Seattle Fine Arts Society (1928-1931) at the age of twenty-one and taught art history courses at the University of Washington.
In 1932, Hatch accepted the position of assistant director of the Isabella Stewart Gardener Museum in Boston, Massachusetts. He also directed the federal Public Works of Art Project in New England. Additionally, Hatch served from 1940-1948 as director of the Albany Institute of Art and History and from 1950-1959 of the Norfolk Museum of Arts and Sciences. Hatch worked as an art advisor for exhibitions at five historically African-American colleges in Atlanta and in San Simeon in California. He founded the American Drawing Annual exhibition.
Hatch conducted extensive research on artists Oscar Bluemner and John Vanderlyn, American silverwork, and American drawing. In addition, Hatch collected American drawings and later donated many of works of art from his personal collection to the National Gallery in Washington, D.C. Aside from his early teaching in Washington state, Hatch taught at the University of Massachusetts and the University of Oregon. He was a member of numerous professional arts-related organizations.
In 1939, Hatch married Olivia Stokes with whom he had four children: Sarah, John, Daniel and James. He died in 1996.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of art historian, collector, educator, and museum administrator John Davis Hatch measure 24.9 linear feet and date from 1790-1995. Within the papers are biographical materials; correspondence; personal business and legal documents; diaries; research, organization and teaching files; writings; printed materials; photographs; and works of art (mostly sketches) by American artists. Research files regarding artists and specific subjects comprise the bulk of this collection.
Scattered biographical materials include an invitation to the Hatch's anniversary party in 1964, short biographical sketches and resumes, certificates, report cards, a silhouette of the Hatch Family circa 1904, and a typecript of a diary written by Olivia Hatch as a child.
Correspondence includes professional correspondence between Hatch and colleagues; letters from family and friends; and some materials regarding exhibitions from the Hatch Collection. The bulk of correspondence spans Hatch's professional career although there are scattered letters from 1915-1943 from Hatch to his parents. Also found are letters addressed to an unidentified "Henry." Correspondence is also found in the research files.
Personal business and financial records consist of inventories, bills, receipts, and other records for artworks purchased, loaned, or donated by Hatch. Also found are records from the J. D. Hatch Associates Cultural Consultants, a draft of Hatch's will, stock and tax materials, and travel papers and passports.
Scattered diaries and journal fragments and a transcript date from 1925-1965. Thirteen "Daily Reflection Journals" date from 1975-1987.
Research files on artists and subjects are extensive, comprising one-half of the collection. Files are varied and may include primary research materials, correspondence, printed materials, notes, and writings. Some of the artists' letters and other materials dated from 1790-early 1800s may have been purchased by Hatch. Among many other items, there is an illustrated letter written by Oscar Bluemner and photographs of Bluemner; primary research materials dating from the early 1800s on John Vanderlyn including a will, receipts, and correspondence; a letter from Rembrandt Peale dated 1830, and an autograph letter from John Trumbull dated 1790. Also found is an index card file.
Organization files contain files and records related to Hatch's affiliations with many cultural organizations. A small amount of teaching and education files consist of Hatch's notes and lectures from the University of Oregon and the University of Massachusetts, and from his continuing education courses he took at St. John's College. Writings and notes include short essays by Hatch, mostly concerning art, exhibitions and museum administration; book reviews; general notes, lists, and reports.
Printed Materials are comprised of exhibition catalogs and announcements, including those from the American Drawing Annual in the 1940s-1950s; printed articles annotated by Hatch; clippings; pricelists; and published works.
A small number of photographs are of Hatch, some by Dorothy Frazer; of his family and friends; and of artists. The bulk of the photographs are of works of art including those owned by Hatch.
Artwork includes two sketchbooks - one by Kenneth Callahan and another by Lloyd McNeill; and additional drawings and sketches by Julian Scott, Henry Kirke Browne, Kenneth Callahan, Ezra Clark, John Cranch, Jasper Francis Crospey, F. O. C. Darley, C. H. Granger, Seymour J. Guy, George Harvey, Edward Lamson Henry, Henry Inman, as well as unsigned or illegible names.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 11 series:
Series 1: Biographical Information, circa 1900-1980s (Box 1; 8 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1903-1990s (Box 1-3; 2 linear feet)
Series 3: Personal Business and Legal Records, Date (Box 3; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 4: Diaries and Journals, 1925-1987 (Box 3, 23; 1.2 linear feet)
Series 5: Research Files, 1790-1992 (Box 3-13, 20-21, 24; 12.7 linear feet)
Series 6: Organization Files, 1930s-1990s (Box 13-14; 1.0 linear feet)
Series 7: Teaching and Education Files, 1930s-1993 (Box 14-15; 1.0 linear feet)
Series 8: Writings and Notes, 1936-1990s (Box 15; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 9: Printed Material, 1870s-1990s (Box 15-19, 22, 25-26, OV1; 5.9 linear feet)
Series 10: Photographs, circa 1900-1990s (Box 22; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 11: Artwork, 1851-1973 (Box 22; 0.3 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Bluemner, Oscar, 1867-1938; Vanderlyn, John, 1775-1852; St. John's College (Annapolis, Md.)--Students; University of Massachusetts--Faculty; University of Oregon--Faculty
Subjects-Topical:
Art, American; Art, American--Study and teaching; Art--Collectors and collecting; Art historians--Massachusetts; Artists--United States; Drawing, American; Painting, American
Types of Materials:
Diaries; Essays; Lectures; Notes; Photographs; Reviews (documents); Sketchbooks; Sketches
Names:
Bluemner, Oscar, 1867-1938; Browne, Henry Kirke; Callahan, Kenneth, 1905-1986; Clark, Ezra; Cranch, John, 1807-1891; Cropsey, Jasper Francis, 1823-1900; Darley, Felix Octavius Carr, 1822-1888; Davies, Arthur B.(Arthur Bowen), 1862-1928; Granger, C. H.; Guy, Seymour J., 1824-1910; Hatch, Olivia Stokes; Harvey, George W., 1855-; Henry, Edward Lamson, 1841-1919; Inman, Henry, 1801-1846; McNeill, Lloyd; Peale, Rembrandt, 1778-1860; Scott, Julian; Trumbull, John, 1756-1843; Vanderlyn, John, 1775-1852
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Information, circa 1900-1980s, Series 1:; (Box 1; 8 folders)
  Found here are materials relating to the Olivia and John Hatch's anniversary party; biographical sketches; certificates from various scholarly, professional, and honorary societies; a diary fragment written by Olivia Hatch as a child; report cards; resumes; and a copy of a silhouette of the Hatch Family from 1904.
  - Anniversary Party, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Sketches, 1930s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Certificates, 1920s-1950s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lists of Activities and Personal Aims, 1940s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Olivia Hatch, circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Report Cards, 1920s-1930s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Resumes, 1930s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Silhouette of the Hatch Family, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1903-1990s, Series 2:; (Box 1-3; 2 linear feet)
  Correspondence is between Hatch and friends, colleagues, family, museums and other organizations. Correspondence is also found in Hatch's research files (series 5.)
  The bulk of the correspondence is arranged by decade only; items have not been further arranged by specific year or month.
  - From Hatch to his Parents, 1915-1943 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Birthday Cards, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Wedding Invitation Replies, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Invitations, 1940s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters to "Henry," circa 1903 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Memoranda, 1930s-1950s (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous, 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1930s, (8 folders) (Box 1, Folder 16-23)
  - 1940s, (9 folders) (Box 1, Folder 24-32)
  - 1950s, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 33-36)
  - 1950s, (5 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
  - 1960s, (12 folders) (Box 2, Folder 6-17)
  - 1970s, (7 folders) (Box 2, Folder 18-34)
  - 1970s, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
  - 1980s, (5 folders) (Box 3, Folder 5-9)
  - 1990s, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 10-12)
  - Undated, circa 1930s-1980s, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 13-16)
- Personal Business and Financial Records, 1934-1994, Series 3:; (Box 3; 0.3 linear feet)
  Personal business and financial records include bills, receipts, inventories, and other records concerning purchases, loans, and donations. Also found are records of J. D. Hatch and Associates, Cultural Cunsultants, and a draft of a will, Selective Service files, stock certificates, tax documents, and passports and travel papers.
  - Bills and Receipts for Artwork, 1930s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Data Discs, circa 1994 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Drawings Collection, 1940-1954, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
  - Insurance Materials, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - J. D. Hatch and Associates, Cultural Consultants, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Last Will and Testament, Draft, circa 1961 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Museum Donations, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Personal Art Inventory, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Receipts, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Selective Service Materials, 1941-1944 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Stock Certificates, 1940s (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Tax Materials, 1935-1938 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Travel Papers and Passports, 1940s-1950s (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Diaries and Journals, 1925-1987, Series 4:; (Box 3, 23; 1.2 linear feet)
  Diary fragments and a transcript date from 1925-1965, and thirteen "Daily Reflection Journals" date from 1975-1987.
  - Fragments, Edited by Hatch, 1934, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Fragments, Edited by Hatch, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Fragments, Transcript, 1934-1939 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Journal, High School, 1925-1926 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Journal, Berkeley, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Pocket Secretary Calendar, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Daily Reflection Journals, 1975-1987, (13 oversized journals housed in Box 23) (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Oversized Daily Reflection Journals, (13 folders) (Box 23, Folder 1-13)
- Research Files, 1790-1992, Series 5:; (Box 3-13, 20-21, 24; 12.7 linear feet)
  The series is arranged as 2 subseries:
  1: Artist Files, 1790-1990s
  2: Subject Files, 1861-1992
  - Artist Files, 1790, circa 1870s-1990s, 1:
    Artist files include correspondence with the artist, collected by Hatch; or about the artist. Additional materials include printed materials and some photographs. There is a substantial amount of material on artists Oscar Bluemner and John Vanderlyn. Files are arranged alphabetically by artist.
    - Adams, Kenneth, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Allston, Washington, 1930s-1950s (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Ames, Ezra, circa 1940s, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 40-41)
    - Ammi, Phillips, 1981, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Arapoff, Alexis Paul, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Archipenko, Alexander, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Arms, John Taylor, 1940s-1950s (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Audobon, John J., circa 1910s (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Ault, George C., 1941-1944 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Barthe, Richmond, 1940s (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Bartlett, William H., 1940s (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Bayne, Armistead, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Beal, Gifford, 1943-1946 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Beard, William Holbrook, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Bearden, Romare, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Bernini, Giovanni Lorenzo, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Bill, Carroll, circa 1950s (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Bladgen, Thomas, circa 1940s (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Bluemner, Oscar, 1914-1965, (11 folders) (Box 4, Folder 1-11)
      (photographs, illustrated letter, letter from Arthur Dove to Bluemner)
    - Bolton, C. K., 1938-1940 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Bolton, Theodore, 1938-1950 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Boucherville, A., 1975 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Brewster, Anna Richards, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Brown, George Irving, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Brown, William Henry, 1940s (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Brown, William Mason, 1940s (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Bush-Brown, Henry Kirke, 1885-1887 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Callahan, Kenneth, 1960s (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Carr, Emily, 1937-1943 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Casado, Julian, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Cole, Thomas, 1820s-1970s (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Colman, Samuel, circa 1940s (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Congdon, William, circa 1948 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Cook, Howard, 1940s-1950s (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Copley, John Singleton, 1820s-1970s, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 27-29)
    - Crite, Allan Rohan, 1938-1939 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Cross, Henry H., circa 1930s (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Davidson, Robert (?), 1941 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Davies, Arthur B., circa 1898 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - de Forest, Lockwood, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Dehn, Adolf, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Dehner, Dorothy, 1944-1952 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Doolittle, Amos, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Dorsey, Thomas, 1940s-1950s (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Doughty, T., 1940s (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Downing, Andrew Jackson, 1930s (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Dows, Olin, 1940s (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Dunbar, A. (?), circa 1930s (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Durchanek, Louis, 1947-1954 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Epstein, Jacob, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Epping, Franc, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Frasconi, Antonio, circa 1950s (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Frazier, Dorothy, 1990s, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 47-48)
    - French, Daniel Chester and Family, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Friedman, Arnold, circa 1950s (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Godefroy, Maximillian, 1816-1819, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Greenough, Horatio, 1938-1960 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Gregoropolus, John, 1960-1963 (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - Griswold, C. C., 1954 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Gropper, William, 1940-1941 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Gross, Chaim, circa 1950s (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Grosz, George, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - Guarducci, Othello, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Harlow, Robert, 1941-1944 (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Haseltine, Herbert, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Heaney, Charles, 1948-1953 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Hitchens, Ivan, 1948-1979 (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Holbrook, Frederick, 1907 (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - Holden, Issac, 1894 (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - Holiday, Henry, 1916-1923 (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Hollyer, S., 1895-1918 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - Homer, Winslow, 1938-1960 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Hopper, Edward (Mrs.), 1941 (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Hoppin, T. F., 1800 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Hosmer, Harriet Goodhue, circa 1870s (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Hovenden, Thomas, 1884 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Howarth, F. M., 1895 (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Huang, Al, 1940s-1960s (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Humphreys, Alexander C., 1907 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - Hunt, Alfred W., circa 1897 (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - Huntington, D., 1901 (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - Hutton, Isaac, 1820, 1940s (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - Innes, George, circa 1880s (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - Innes, George Jr., 1924 (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - Ives, Chauncey Bradley, 1872-1873 (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - Jacques, Russell, 1970s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - Jarvis, John Wesley, 1939-1960 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Joseflin (?), Isaac, 1900s (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Jones, H. Bolton, 1905, 1925-1927 (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Katz, Leo, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Kent, Rockwell, 1945-1955 (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - LaFarge, John, 1930s-1949 (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - LaFarge, Thomas, 1940s (Box 4, Folder 88)
    - Lathrop, Dorothy and Gertrude, 1943, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - Latrobe, Benjamin Henry, 1950s (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Lauck, Rev. Anthony J., 1958-1961 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Leutze, Emanuel, 1940-1946 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Lewy, Fred, 1946-1949 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Littlefield, William H., 1941 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Loggie, Helen, 1950s (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Malbone, Edward G., 1938-1952 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Martin, Homer, 1940-1961 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Mauer, Louis, 1930s (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - McNeill, Lloyd, 1960s (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Morris, Carl, 1949-1958 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Morris, George L. K., circa 1950s (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Morris, Jay Scott, 1946-1947 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Morse, Samuel F. B., 1940s (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Moskowitz, Ira, 1960s, 1978, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 15-16)
    - Moses, Grandma, circa 1940s (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Mount, William S., 1940-1960 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Myers, Jerome, 1939-1941 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Neagle, John, 1866, 1940-1956 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Newton, Roger Hale, 1948-1949 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Palmer Family, Erastus Dow and Walter Launt, 1856, 1942-1950s (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Patridge, Roi, 1940-1962 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Peale Family, Rembrant, Angelo, Washington, 1830, 1893, 1938-1958 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Perkins, Elizabeth Ward, 1930s-1940s (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Powers, [illegible], circa 1880s (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Price, C. S., 1940-1960 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Refregier, Anton, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Saint-Memin, Fevret de, 1940-1962 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Sargent, John Singer, 1925-1930s (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Sekiya, Ungai, 1950s (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Sheeler, Charles, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Sibley, Charles, 1954-1958 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Slobodkin, Louis, 1940s (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Smith, Vernon, 1930s (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Sopher, Aaron, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Stankiewicz, Richard, 1980s (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Sterner, Albert, 1940s (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Stow, Charles Messer, 1947-1964 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Stuart, Gilbert, 1920s (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Tack, Augustus Vincent, 1930s, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Tait, Arthur Fitzwilliam, 1930s (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Talbot, Jesse, circa 1840s (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Train, Arthur C. (and Mrs.), 1943-1944 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Trumbull, John, 1790, 1937-1955 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Tuttle, Macowin, 1957-1960 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Twitchell, Alston, circa 1930s (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Vanderlyn, John, 1808-1840s, 1940s-1990s, (9 folders) (Box 5, Folder 48-56)
      (primary materials, printed material, correspondence, notes, dissertation)
    - Vanderlyn, John 1808-1840s, 1940s-1990s, (30 folders) (Box 6, Folder 1-30)
      (notes, writings, correspondence)
    - Vanderlyn, John, 1808-1840s, 1940s-1990s, (20 folders) (Box 7, Folder 1-20)
      (printed material)
    - Vanderlyn, John, 1808-1840s, 1940s-1990s, (44 folders) (Box 8, Folder 1-44)
    - Van Zandt, William, 1942-1968 (Box 8, Folder 45)
    - Ward, John Quincey Adams, 1880s (Box 8, Folder 46)
    - West, Benjamin, 1930s-1960s (Box 8, Folder 47)
    - Whitelaw, Robert, 1940s-1960s (Box 8, Folder 48)
    - Whittredge, Worthington, 1892-1908 (Box 8, Folder 49)
    - Williams, Keith Shaw, 1941-1951 (Box 8, Folder 50)
    - Winkler, John W., 1979 (Box 8, Folder 51)
    - Woodruff, Hale, 1946-1947 (Box 8, Folder 52)
    - Woods, Arthur, circa 1970s (Box 8, Folder 53)
    - Illegible, 1885 (Box 8, Folder 54)
  - Subject Files, 1861-1992, Subseries 2:
    Subjects files either concern topics of interest or research, or may contain correspondence with the named subject, such as museums, or contain correspondence about the named topic. Index Card Files are located at the end of this subseries and contain Hatch's alphabetized research notes regarding portraits and bibliography of his research.
    - Albany, New York, 1990-1991 (Box 8, Folder 55)
    - American Architecture, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 8, Folder 56)
    - American Art and Artists, 1950s (Box 8, Folder 57)
    - American Artists Depository Plan, 1960s (Box 8, Folder 58)
    - American Drawings Collection, 1940s-1960s, (3 folders) (Box 8, Folder 59-61)
    - American Drawings Collection, 1940s-1960s, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
    - American Museum of Natural History Discovery Tours, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - American Silverworks, 1940s-1950s (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Ames, Winslow, 1930s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Amigos de Machu Pichu, 1960s (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Andrew Jackson Downing Memorial, 1930s-1940s (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Anson Phelps Stokes Estate, 1900-1915, 1960s, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 8-9)
      (concerning Cecilia Beaux portrait)
    - "Antique Arts," 1960s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 10)